各位大人
My lords
王后擅自离席
in the absence of the queen herself,
本庭宣判其违反法庭命令
whom this tribunal has pronounced contumacious,
既然王后传唤时缺席
since she does not appear when summoned,
本庭将试图裁决
we are trying to determine whether or not
其与亚瑟王子的第一次婚姻
her first marriage to prince arthur was
是否有过真正的肉体关系
in fact consummated incarnal copula.
传证人
We call a witness:
安东尼-威勒比先生
Sir anthony willoughby.
我清楚你一直护送
I understand you were in the escort
亚瑟王子步入婚床
taking prince arthur to the nuptial bed?
是的 大人
I was, sir.
我的父亲当时是国王家仆的主事
My father was at the time steward of the king's household.
所以我在场见证了王子…
So I was present when the prince was...
进入了凯瑟琳女士的… 床
inserted into lady katherine's bed.
早上醒来的时候也是如此
And also when he woke in the morning.
你早上见到王子的时候
And did the prince say anything to you
他可曾对你说过什么？
when you saw him in the morning?
是的 大人 他说
Yes, sir. He said:
"威勒比 我很渴 给我一杯麦芽酒"
"Willoughby, I'm thirsty. Bring me a cup of ale.
"昨晚我深入了西班牙腹地"
Last night I was in the midst of spain. "
肃静
Silence!
禁止喧哗
Silence in the court!
还有别的吗？
Anything else?
是的 先生 那天晚些时候他又对我们说
Yes, sir. Later that day he said to us:
"诸位 找个老婆是一项好消遣"
"Masters, it's a good pastime to have a wife. "
法庭禁止喧哗
Silence in the court!
我相信我们有那条沾血的床单
I believe we may have the bloodstained sheets
可以确证先王的真实事迹
to corroborate my lord's story.
这是最有力的证据 主教大人 最能说明问题
That would be most useful,your eminence. Most useful.
王后陛下
Your majesty.
先生们
Gentlemen.
国王质问您为何离庭
King asks why You are not in court.
我已经表明我的答案与立场
I have given answer to that already.
能否进一步说话？
Could we go somewhere private?
为什么？我没什么见不得人的事
Why? I have nothing to hide.
让我的女仆们还有整个世界 听您大放厥词吧
Let my ladies and the whole world hear what you have to say.
国王命令您在这件事上…
The King commands that you surrender...
完全臣服于他
this whole matter into his hands.
否则法庭会判您有罪
Otherwise the court will condemn you.
听到这个请求我真是惊讶万分
I am surprised to receive such a request
尤其是您这样一位贤明高贵的大人
from such a wise and noble man as you.
我只是一个可怜的女人
I am but a poor woman,
失去了智慧 失去了理解力
lacking both in wit and understanding.
我该如何回应…
How am I supposed to respond to such
这个突然提出的请求？
a request made to me out of the blue?
您完全明白国王的意愿
You know perfectly well what the king desires
您也清楚他有什么想法
and what he shall have.
我只知道 主教大人 是你…
All I know, eminence,is that you,
出于私欲 煽风点火
for your own purposes,have kindled this fire.
每时每刻 每年每月
All this time,all these years,
我也曾怀疑过 你清高的傲慢和虚伪的荣耀
I have wondered at your high pride and your vain glory.
我憎恶你骄奢淫逸
I have abhorred your voluptuous life and had no regard
我蔑视你恃强凌弱 专横独行
at all for your presumptuous power and your tyranny!
我也知道你怨恨我侄子罗马皇帝
I know also your malice against my nephew the emperor.
恨之入骨 如同蛇蝎
You hate him like a scorpion.
为什么呢？
And why?
因为他未曾满足你的野心
Because he would not satisfy your ambition
未曾强行让你登上教皇宝座
and make you pope by force.
夫人 你绝对不能凭空认定…
Madam, You should never presume to know-
我唯一的快感就是挫败你
My only satisfaction is that in frustrating you
把你从国王的宠爱中快点拉下马
I hasten your fall from the king's good graces
我只要这个结果 为此不惜一切
an outcome I desire above all others.
主教大人请停步
Hold, Your eminence.
走这条路无法达成离婚
You will not get your divorce this way.
但我们已经无路可走
It is the only way.
朋友 我要喝酒
Friend! Give me a drink!
渴死了
I'm thirsty!
你们要是像我昨天晚上那样
If you'd all been to spain as many times
一连几次跨进西班牙
as I went there last night,
你们也会渴得要死
you'd all be fucking thirsty too!
插 抽 插 抽 插 抽
In, out,in, out, in out!
我告诉你啊 小伙子
And I'll tell you this, lads:
我第一次和女人睡觉的时候
First time I lay with a lady
完全是黄毛小子 什么都不懂
I was but a chit of a lad.
我的小老二翘得有这么高
So high to a grasshopper I was.
我干了她一整晚…
I poked her all night...
干杯 我说 敬一杯酒
A toast!I say, a toast
为凯瑟琳皇后干杯
to queen katherine!
她不屈不饶 上帝保佑她
Who doesn't give a fig!God bless her!
为英格兰皇后干杯
To the queen of england!
国王陛下到
His majesty, the king!
各位大人
My lords.
陛下
Majesty.
真华丽
Splendid.
我的眼线刚刚告诉我
So my sources have just told me
罗马皇帝坚信沃尔西
that the emperor believes wolsey
就是鼓动离婚的罪魁祸首
is to blame for instigating the divorce.
他相信英格兰人民
He believes that the people of england
会马上起义 把那个禽兽送上绞架
will soon rise up and bring that creature to the scaffold.
他死期不远矣
His end is surely approaching.
那之后 大人您
After which, your grace
将会成为宫廷的首要人物
will be the first man at court
实至名归
as you ought to be.
这样的话 博林
In which case, boleyn,
我绝对会扩大你的家族利益
I shan't fail to promote your family's interests.
千真万确 你已经位高权重
It's true you've risen high.
不过还可以再高
But you shall rise higher yet.
你发现了吗？
did You see?
他们都在看你
They were all looking at you.
我很高兴 我要他们都看你
I'm glad. I want them to look at you.
我要他们嫉妒
I want them to be envious.
我要所有人都知道
I want all of them to know
我有多么爱你
exactly how much I love you.
然后就像我的家族格言所说 我拥有"无上的荣福"
Then, like My family motto I am "the most happy. "
今天法庭进展如何？
How did it go in court today?
很好
Well enough.
凯瑟琳仍然拒绝出席
Yet katherine refuses to attend.
这无关紧要了
It will make no difference.
沃尔西许诺我夏天就可离婚
Wolsey promises me I'll have a divorce by summer.
许诺容易 兑现困难
Promises are easy.
如果你不能离婚呢？
What if you don't?
玛格丽特 怎么了？
Margaret, what is it?
我睡不着
I couldn't sleep.
回到床上来 天很冷
Come back to bed. It's cold.
等一阵
Not yet.
明天我要出庭 你去吗？
I'm going to court tomorrow. Will you come?
你的兄长又一次要求你出席
Your brother has asked,again, for your presence.
我说得很清楚了
I told you.
我不要看到他如此公开的
Not while he makes love in
和那个叫博林的女人 眉来眼去
public to that boleyn girl.
这件事情如此令人生厌 把他变成了一个傻瓜
It's offensive and it makes him look like a fool.
明眼人都能看出…
Everyone else can see how...
博林一家多么狂妄和贪婪 他怎么就看不出来？
proud and grasping the boleyns are. Why can't he?
假如他命令你出席呢？
what if He commands you to come?
这是干吗？
What is this?
一个妻子看着她的丈夫
only a wife to a husband.
睡吧 我亲爱的查尔斯
Sleep now, my sweet charles.
我为你祈祷 安睡吧
I pray you,sleep.
法庭肃静
Silence in the court!
在王后缺席的情况下
in the absence of the queen,
她的顾问菲舍主教请求我们
we have been asked by her council, bishop fisher,
在本庭发表声明
to make a statement to this court.
既然如此 我们决定
In the circumstances we have decided
准许发言
that such a statement is admissible.
阁下
Your grace.
法官大人 诸位身负
Our honours,you have been asked to give verdict...
为这段王室婚姻的合法性做出裁决 的重任
on the validity of the royal marriage.
阁下们 在下的观点是
Sirs, it is my contention that this marriage
国王与王后的婚姻不能 被任何强势所拆散
of the king and queen can be dissolved by no power,
无论强加拆散的是凡人 还是神力
human or divine!
让我们… 让我…
Let'S... let me give,
如果可以的话… 为大家复述一段平行经文
if I might, a biblical parallel.
我坚信你们会记得
You will remember, I am sure,
暴君希律王…
the tyrant herod antipas...
暴君 暴君
Tyrant, tyrant.
抛弃自己的妻子
... Who disembarrassed himself of his wife
为了占有他的弟媳
in order that he might take his brother's wife.
然后当施洗约翰(耶稣的表兄) 敢于指责这对王室夫妻的时候
And who then executed john the baptist
希律王就处死了施洗约翰
when he dared to criticize the royal couple.
正如如施洗约翰一般
Just as john the baptist, so I,
我怀拥人类的谦卑 向高高在上的你们宣布
in all humility,say to you here today
我已经准备好用我的生命为代价
that I am ready to lay down my life,
用我的生命为代价 去捍卫婚姻的神圣不可侵犯
to lay down my life,to defend the sanctity
去声讨可耻的通奸
of marriage and to condemn adultery!
蛮不讲理
Outrageous!
法官大人
Your honours.
我控诉这个人 菲舍主教
I accuse this man,bishop fisher,
控诉他的傲慢 鲁莽与背信弃义
of arrogance, temerity and disloyalty!
我强烈要求 不要理会这一派胡言
I demand that you disregard every vile word.
托马斯 你来了 来一杯？
Ah, thomas. Come in. Drink?
不用了 谢谢
Not for me,thank you.
不客气
No.
有个任务要托付余你 托马斯
I have a mission for you, thomas.
法国和罗马帝国军队已经停火
The french and imperial forces have ceased their aggression.
将会有会议
There is to be some sort of conference
在法国的康比亚召开
at a place called cambria, in france,
有双方谈判代表
between their negotiators and
以及罗马教皇的代表人参加
also with representatives of the pope.
我肯定无法参加
I of course, am unable to attend.
托马斯 关键是
The vital thing, thomas,
法国和罗马帝国两方不能达成一致
is that there be no agreement between the other 2 parties.
我已经私下得到法国国王的保证
I've had private reassurances from the king of france
他毕竟是我们的盟友
who is after all, our ally that he will never make
无论如何他也不会和罗马皇帝达成和解
peace with the emperor,under any circumstances.
同样 教皇和罗马皇帝
Similarly, there must be no rapprochement
也没可能和解
between the holy father and the emperor.
你要明白 在这种情况下
You must understand,under those circumstances,
让教皇满足国王陛下的愿望 是没有可能的
it would be impossible for the pope to grant the king his desire.
是的 我的确明白
Yes, I do understand.
现在…
Now...
你有你的原则
you have your principles,
我理解
I understand that.
但出于我们二人对国王的爱
But for the love we both have for the king,
但你得在康比亚尽可能 加以阻止
your job at cambria is to be as obstructive as possible.
千万别让弗朗西斯违背 对我们许下的承诺
Don't let francis renege on his commitments to us
也别让教皇忘了
and don't let the pope forget
是查尔斯的军队 入侵并洗劫了罗马
that it was charles' forces that invaded and sacked rome.
哦 还有件事
Oh. And there is one other thing?
除此之外？
More than this?
暗地里透过那边的密探打探
Try to discover, by subtle means, through
看看罗马皇帝是否准备
his agents,if the emperor is prepared to
通过武力支持他的姑姑
support his aunt by use of force.
你认为他会为了支持皇后而入侵英格兰？
You think He might invade england in support of the queen?
我没有"认为"任何事
I don't think anything.
而是考虑到各个方面
But I imagine everything.
正是那些顾虑让我痛苦 Thomas
And it is those imaginings that cause me great pain, thomas.
相当痛苦
Great pain.
你不是说过吗
But wasn't it you that said
没有人可以
no man can expect to go to
轻易就上天堂？
heaven on a feather bed?
你就没点好话说吗？
Ave you nokind things to say?
好话？
Kind?
对你的妻子说
to Your wife.
对你孩子的母亲说
The mother of your child!
你在公众面前对我百般羞辱
You treat me so unkindly and in public negle
凯瑟琳 你必须面对现实
katherine, You must accept the inevitable!
大部分高层舆论都反对我们在一起
The weight of academic opinion is against us.
我们本就不是合法夫妻
We were never legally man and wife.
教庭会按照我的意志裁决
And the court will decide in my favour.
如果他们不遵从我的意愿
And if the court does not decide in my favour,
我将如异教徒般违抗教皇 并同我心爱的女人结婚
I shall denounce the pope as a heretic and marry whom I please.
亲爱的…
Sweetheart...
当我初次与您共寝的时候 是个有天使陪伴的处女
by all the angels I was intact when I came to your bed.
行了 你就他妈的是个处女
Alright!So You were a fucking virgin!
那不是关键
That's not the point!
我不是告诉过你 如果你和皇后争吵
Did I Not tell You that if You argued with the queen
她肯定会占上风
she'd be sure to have the upper hand?!
是的 但… 总有一天
Yes, but...one fine morning
你会被她的那番道理说服 遗弃我
you'll succumb to her reasoning and cast me off!
你到底想说什么？
what do You mean?
安 我爱你
Anne, I love you.
放开我 放开我
Let me go! Let me go!
你为什么不明白？
Why don't you see?
为什么就是不懂？
Why can't you understand?
我已经等了那么久 为了什么？
I've been waiting for so long. For what?!
我原本可能已经有了一桩好婚事
In the meantime I could have contracted
生儿育女
some advantageous marriage,and borne sons,
这是女人一生向往的
which is a woman's greatest consolation in this life.
但现在浪费我的时间 我的青春
But instead I've been wasting my time and my youth.
毫无意义
For no purpose at all!
安 别这样
Anne, stop this!
你会有儿子
You will have sons!
我们会有儿子
We will have sons!
不 不 太迟了
No!No. It's too late.
你妻子不会放过你 我早该明白
Your wife won't let you go. I should have realized.
你去哪儿？
Where areou going?
回家
Home.
留下来 我求你了 安
Stay here, I beg you. Anne!
我是英格兰的国王
I'm the king of england!
速速让路
Make way for his grace!
让让
Make way!
主教大人
Your eminence.
谢谢
Grazie, Grazie, grazie.
教皇送来的急件
An urgent message from the pope.
谢谢你 年轻人
Thank You, kind sir.
瞧 他总得依靠别人
Look! He's always leaning on someone.
也许有人得依靠他
Perhaps Someone should lean on him.
也许吧
Perhaps.
主教大人
Your eminence.
陛下
majesty.
我相信马上就会公布裁决
I trust we will soon have a verdict.
的确如此
Indeed.
听到德国发生的事 我们很悲痛
we hear with great distress of events in germany.
教堂被破坏的事
The destruction of the churches.
是个悲惨事件 陛下
Melancholy events, majesty.
但为什么会发生这样的事？
but why is it happening?
陛下的意思是？
Majesty?
我来告诉你
I'll tell you.
路德教看中罗马的弱点
The lutherans attack what they
就会对其进行攻击
see as the wickedness of rome.
他们相信腐败受人推崇
They believe corruption is rewarded,
而信仰已经被遗弃 被置之不理
but the faithful are abandoned and badly treated.
我是个虔诚的人 主教大人
I am a man of faith,your eminence.
上帝不会任由教皇 违背我的意愿
God forbid his holiness should ever turn his back on me.
陛下
My lord.
你不感到厌烦吗 查尔斯？
Don't you ever gettired of it, charles?
当然会
Of course.
厌倦了就到头大睡
Then I go to sleep.
我敢打赌你一定也梦到女人
I bet youdream of women too.
不
No.
我梦见上帝
I dream of god.
梦见天堂与地狱 在梦中忏悔
Of heavenand hell and of repentance.
既然你这么问
Since you asked.
想什么呢 安东尼？
What are youthinking, anthony?
听着歌曲 想着那句 "Omnia vincit amor"
I'm listening tothe song and I'm thinking: Omnia vincit amor.
"Omnia vincit amor" 没人能抵挡爱情的力量
Omnia vincit amor, "no one can resist love".
大人
My lord.
陛下
Majesty.
请让安回到宫里
Please ask anne to come back to court.
我衷心的请求您
I beg you for my sake.
我不能没有她
I can't live without her.
明天裁决将会宣布 我也将自由
Tomorrow I shall have my verdict and I shall be free.
是 陛下
Majesty.
各位主教大人 根据此高等法庭的规则
Eminences,in accordance with the rules and
及陛下的个人意愿
laws of this tribunal and the wishes of his majesty,
请您正式宣布裁决
I ask you officially to deliver your judgment.
陛下… 各位大人
Your majesty... my lords.
经过慎重考虑 我们决定
After much deliberation,we have decided that
这一事件过于重大
this great matter is too important to be here decided
需要经由罗马元老院审视后进行裁决
without consultation with the curia at rome.
不巧的是 元老院正值夏季休会
Unfortunately, the curia is now in summer recess.
因此 别无他法
In which case there is no alternative
只能将此案推延至10月1日
but to prorogue thistribunal until october 1st.
这就是我们的裁决
That is our judgment.
蠢货
You stupid cunt!
上帝为证 自从你担任英格兰的红衣主教
By god, it has never been good to be in england while
英格兰就没一天好日子
we've have cardinals among us!
你真的人为这一切都是我的罪过？
Are you so dense that you really think this is my doing?!
所有人中
And of all people,
你是最不该对红衣主教如此无理的人
you have the least cause to be offended by cardinals!
如果不是我这个小小的红衣主教 时不时为你说好话
If it wasn't for me,a simple cardinal,sometimes having praised you,
你早就人头不保了
you would no longer have a head on your shoulders!
多好的一天
Happy day
是的 蒙多萨大人
aaa
坎佩吉奥从教皇那里收到秘密指示
aaaa
他提议将离婚案交由罗马元老院处理
aaaaa
我没有被抛弃
aaaaaa
罗马皇帝一直在为您的事 不知疲倦的奔走
aaaaaaa
你真的要走了？
Is it true you are leaving?
是的 皇后陛下
Yes, your majesty.
查普大使将替代我
Ambassador chapuys will replace me.
我知道他
I know him.
他是最值得信赖的人
He's a mosttrustworthy person
会尽心尽力维护您的权益
and will take up your defense with all fidelity and diligence.
正如您一样 蒙多萨大人
As you have done,senor mendoza.
这个送给您
Toman esto.
留个纪念
In memory of me.
陛下
majestad.
托马斯 看到你真高兴
Thomas, how verygood to see you.
国王怎么样？
How is the king?
国王将要巡游
The king is ah... going on a progress.
立即出发
Immediately.
和安女士同行
With the lady anne.
我明白了
I see.
请告诉陛下 我将立即把达拉谟教区的
Tell his majesty that I am handing over to him
所有税收上交给他
at once the entire revenues of the see of durham.
那是英格兰最富有的地区
It is one of the richest in england.
告诉他 我将继续为他的事而努力
And tell him I shall not cease to work for his great matter.
坎佩吉奥和我会努力达成他的心愿 明白？
Campeggio and I will gladly accomplish his lawful desire. Do you see?
我会告诉他的
I shall tell him.
托马斯
And thomas.
告诉我 我能指望你 为我在国王面前说些好话吗？
tell me I can trust you to advocate my interests to the king.
放心 没有你 我还只是个文员
You ma for without you, I would be a lowly clerk,
毫无收益 毫无前途
without profit or future.
我的一生都是欠你的
I owe you my life.
罗马教廷召我去
I've been summoned to rome.
我得去见教皇 亲自解决我的问题
I have to appear before the pope and answer for myself.
能想象吗？
Can you imagine it?
我？英格兰国王 除了上帝之外 不会听从任何势力的摆布
Me?The king of england, who answers to no authority but god!
该死的沃尔西
Damn wolsey.
诅咒他下地狱
Damn him to hell.
我可否直言两句？
May I speak plainly?
可以
Yes, of course.
有些势力认为不该听从教皇的安排
There are some who on good authority care not for popes.
那些作家写道 国王在自己的王国里
These writers say that the king is both emperor
既是帝王又是绝对的教皇
and pope absolutely in his own kingdom.
什么作家？
Which writers?
请允许我给你看本书
I have a book to show you, with your permission.
给我看
Show it to me.
轻柔的爱意 爱的轻盈
Softly love and to love softly.
如枫树枝头的露珠
Dew on the sycamore branch.
我的心 飞奔过吱吱作响的大门
By the creaking gate where my heart hurries afterwards
穿过麦田 穿过石南丛中
through the path of wheat along the briar,
直至掩埋我的那片地方…
to that stone.	.	.	 under which I lie.
感谢您的接见 陛下
Thank you for the audience, your majesty.
很好 大人们
Very well, my lords.
陛下
Majesty.
罗切福大人？
Lord rochford?
陛下 西班牙国王新派的大使 查普大人
Majesty, the new imperial ambassador, mr. Chapuys,
请求您允许他向皇后表达他的敬意
asks permission to present his credentials to the queen.
批准
Granted.
大人 还有其他事么？
My lord, is there anything else?
陛下 坎佩吉奥主教要回罗马
Majesty, cardinal campeggio is returning to rome
想要跟您正式提交辞呈
and would like to take his formal leave of your majesty.
很好
Very well.
克伦威尔先生
Mr. Cromwell.
请他到格莱夫顿宫殿来 叫上沃尔西
Invite him here to grafton house. Also wolsey.
还有其他事么？
Anything else?
大人 有什么事么？
Your grace?
陛下 请您原谅
Majesty, forgive me.
马格利特去世了
Margaret is dead.
死于肺病
She died of consumption.
你从未跟我说过她病了
you never even told me she was sick.
她是国王的妹妹 怎么国王不来这？
If that's the king's sister, why isn't the king here?
国王不能参加葬礼
The king cannot go to funerals.
为什么？
Why?
谁也不许想象国王驾崩的场景
No one is allowed to imagine the death of the king.
那是叛国之罪
For that would be treason.
你那么关心我
you cared for me.
对不起
I'm sorry.
过来 过来 托马斯
Come, come, thomas!
告诉我结果怎样
Tell me what happened.
你是不是准时到达康比亚？
I take it you arrived at cambria on time?
不完全是
Not exactly.
我们晚了一周
We were a week late.
一周？
A week?
那你们还怎么参与正式的谈判？
Then how could you possibly have contributed to the substantive arguments?
我们做不到
We couldn'T.
我们无法参与关键问题的讨论
We weren't privy to the main discussions.
我们只被允许参与 几大党派的周边问题讨论
We were only able to enter into peripheral negotiations with the major parties.
都谈了什么？
What negotiations?
很高兴向您汇报 我们成功的保住了
Well, I'm happy to report that we secured a return to mutually
我们与低地国家互利业务关系中的盈利
beneficial trade relations between ourselves and the low countries.
我们同样获得了罗马皇帝
We also obtained guarantees regarding long-standing
长期向国王进贡的保证
payments owing to the king by the emperor.
那关键的议题呢 托马斯
But the major disputes, thomas!
关键的议题 结果怎样？
The major disputes! What happened?
法国国王拒绝讲和么？
Did the king of france refuse to make peace?
不
No.
相反 他和解了与罗马皇帝之间 的所有分歧
On the contrary he settled all his differences with the emperor
而且双方也都解决了与教皇之间的分歧
and both of them then settled their differences with his holiness pope clement.
换而言之 他们故意将我们孤立
In other words, we were deliberately sidelined.
如果你偏要这么说的话
If you choose to put it like that.
那么 教皇也就没可能准许 国王的离婚
Now there is no chance that the pope will give the king his divorce.
告诉我 托马斯
Tell me, thomas.
你认为你在康比亚到底 完成了何等功绩
what exactly do you think you might have achieved at cambria,
让你看起来如此的自鸣得意？
that makes you look so smug?
主教大人 恕我非意
With respect your eminence, to some degree
我这次去不是为了完成 什么功绩
it wasn't for me to achieve anything
我认为这次外交某种意义上是成功的
yet I consider this diplomacy to be somewhat successful.
欧洲再次和平了
Once more there is peace in europe.
英格兰和罗马帝国和好了
England is at peace with the empire.
更为重要的是 教皇的权威再次树立 并得到了认可
More importantly, papal authority is restored and recognized.
这正是我所坚信的
That is what I believe in.
弗朗西斯背叛了我
Francis betrayed me.
弗朗西斯看到了战争了无用
Francis saw the futility of war.
他认可遵循传统的必要性
He recognized the need for tradition.
而你 托马斯
And you, thomas.
你毁了我
you have destroyed me.
让路
Make way!
阁下 这边请
This way, your excellency.
主教大人 这是您的房间
Your honour's chamber.
谢谢
Thank you.
等等 等等 我的房间呢？
Wait. Wait! Where is my chamber?
主教大人 没有为您准备
There is none prepared for you, your eminence.
但… 我必须换下我的骑马服
But... I must change from my riding clothes.
那你最好问问别处
Then you had best ask elsewhere.
阁下
Your eminence.
哦 诺里斯先生？
Ah, mr.Norris?
你可以用我的房间
Use my room.
虽然不大 但… 我会把您的行李安置好
It's not much, but... I'll have your trunk sent up.
换好衣服后 你要去会客厅
When you've changed you are to go to the presence chamber.
十分感激 诺里斯
I am grateful to you, norris.
阁下 这里有很多人都对您心存感激
There are many here, sir, who have cause to be grateful to you.
尽管他们有时候并不表现出来
Though alas, they do not show it.
红衣主教沃尔西和坎佩吉奥参见
cardinals wolsey and campeggio.
听说您身体欠佳 是真的么？
I hear you've been unwell. Is it true?
陛下 我何时因身体欠佳 而未能向您效忠？
Majesty, when was I ever unwell enough not to serve you?
这正是我所想的
That's what I thought!
这些人 他们说谎
They tell such lies, these people.
我能相信谁？
Who can I trust?
主教大人 你和我 我们经历风雨一路走来
We've come a long way together, you and I, cardinal.
你认为我会忘记吗
Did you think I'd forget?
需要做的还有很多
And there is still a great deal more to do.
我明白 我明白
I know, I know.
不要害怕
Don't be afraid.
我们明天可以好好谈谈
We shall talk properly tomorrow.
早上好 甜心
good morning sweetheart.
躲开 我有话要对国王讲
Stand aside. I must speak with the king.
让开
Stand aside!
陛下
Your majesty!
Majesty!
陛下
Your majesty!
陛下 陛下 陛下
Majesty! Majesty! Majesty!
查普大使
Ambassador chapuys.
陛下
Your majesty.
罗马皇帝派我来向您呈上委任书
I have come at the king's invitation to present my credentials from the emperor.
这边请
Please.
很高兴见到你
I am glad to see you.
要知道 在这乱世下你接受这个任务
You know your mission has fallen at a complicated time.
千真万确
Indeed.
皇后 我从未视自己的任务为难事
I see my mission, madam, as one oftoute douceur.
说的好
All sweetness!
请问殿下 我是否该同时将委任状
May I ask your highness if I should now, at once,
呈交给红衣主教沃尔西？
also present my credentials to his eminence cardinal wolsey?
跟以前相比 我看现在没有这个必要
I do not see that there is such a need as before.
主教某种程度上已经… 失宠了
The cardinal is somewhat... undone.
他已经被进入跨入宫廷
He has been refused permission to attend court.
那我应该去拜访谁？
Then who should I attend instead?
诺福克 萨福克和罗切福
Norfolk, suffolk and rochford.
他们现在是国王的近臣 掌管日常事务
they are now closest to the king, and carry out his affairs.
如果你想了解内情 就去拜访他们
Seek them out if you would know things.
但你同样要知道 大使大人 他们并不是我的朋友
Me but you should also know ambassador, that they are no great friends of mine.
任何一个都不是 应该说…
Any of them. In fact better to say,
他们都是我的死敌
they are all my mortal enemies.
让开
Make way!
沃尔西主教
Cardinal wolsey!
你被控蔑视王权罪
You are here charged with praemunire:
在国王的领土擅用罗马主教的权力
That is exercising your powers of papal legate in the king's realm,
因而诋毁了国王的权威
thus derogating the king's lawful authority.
你被免除一切职务
You are to be dismissed of all your offices
你的财物将交与国王手中
and all your goods shall be taken into the king's hands.
你们是否有国王亲手起草的文书？
I take it you have the king's written authority for this?
你被命交出你的文印
You are commanded to relinquish the great seal of your office.
我要去哪？
And where am I to go?
你将被驱逐至国王杰瑞克的宅子
To the king's house at jericho.
等待审判的裁决
To await the verdict of the court.
快给尊敬的大人让路
Make way for his lord's grace there!
现在给我们祈祷一下 如何 大人？
How 'bout a blessing now, your eminence?
我永远眷爱的克伦威尔
My own eternally beloved cromwell,
我恳求你 如果你深深敬爱着我 就应为我做任何事情
I beseech you, as you love me and will ever do anything for me,
你今天的工作一完成 就马上来看我
come here today, as soon as your work is finished,
不要理其他事情
and forgetting everything else.
不单是为了我的释然 而求见于你
For I would not only communicate things to you
同样也能给予你由衷并悲痛
for my own comfort and relief, but would also have your good,
并缜密的忠告
sad, discreet advice and counsel.
星期六 用我颤抖的双手
In haste, this saturday,
和悲切的心草写此书
with the rude hand and sorrowful heart of your assured who loves you.
沃尔西
Wolsey.
沃尔西承认了对他所有的指控
Wolsey pleaded guilty to all the charges made against him.
是的 我听说了
Yes I heard.
他被判决入狱了
And sentenced to prison.
我废除了对他的处罚
I have rescinded his punishment.
我甚至同意保留他的约克主教的头衔
I've even agreed to let him keep the bishopric of york,
还支付他3000安格尔的养老金
with a pension of 3000 angels.
你看我这算是个什么"魔鬼"？
You see what kind of monster I am?
我需要委任一个新的议政大臣
I need to appoint a new chancellor.
一个我能信任的人
Someone I can trust.
你学过法律和皇室礼仪
You're trained as a lawyer and in royal service.
你也有国际威望
You have international prestige.
你是伊拉兹马斯的朋友 全英格兰至高的人道主义者
The friend of erasmus, the greatest humanist in all england.
你有敏锐细腻的头脑
You have a fine, sharp mind.
不
No.
不什么
No what!
不 我不想成为议政大臣
No, I don't want to be chancellor.
你必须按照我的命令去做
You will do as I command!
听着 托马斯
Listen thomas.
我知道你在我的离婚问题上颇有顾虑
I know you have scruples concerning my divorce.
我向你保证
And I swear to you,
这件事只会交给在良心上能接受此事 的人来处理
it will only be dealt with by those whose consciences agree with it.
我只要你处理其他的事项
I'll only use you for other things
我绝不让此事困扰你的良心
and I will never let it molest your conscience.
听着… 汤姆
look... tom.
我希望 并且命令你 你将来的所作所为
I want you, nay I command you, in all the things that you do.
要看在上帝的份上 也要看在我的份上
to look to god first, and only then to me.